Guide to the Mooney-Billings Case Collection MS 016
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Mooney-Billings Case Collection
1917-1938
Western Connecticut State University Archives and Special Collections
Craig, Leonard
MS 016
127
2.25 Linear Feet, 2 boxes
Thomas Mooney (1892-1942) was a labor leader involved in several violent labor struggles in California before 1916. He was convicted and jailed as a participant in the bomb killings at the San Francisco Preparedness Day Parade in 1916. The collection includes documentation of the ongoing effort to exonerate Mooney.
Provenance
Professor Herb Janick is believed to have acquired these materials in the 1970s from an unknown source. The creator of the collection is assumed to be Leonard Craig (1986-1973) who lived in Danbury at the end of his life; however, there is no documentation that these were Craig's papers.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Thomas Mooney (1892-1942) was an active labor leader in several labor struggles that turned violent in California before 1916. He was convicted and jailed as a participant in the bomb killings at the San Francisco Preparedness Day Parade in 1916. Five persons including Mooney and Warren Billings were arrested for the crime but only Mooney and Billings were convicted. Mooney was sentenced to hang and Billings to life imprisonment. Mooney's case aroused international interest because of the widely held belief in his innocence and the confessions of perjured testimony at his trial. California Governor William D. Stephens, at the behest of President Woodrow Wilson, commuted Mooney's sentence to life imprisonment in November 1918.
Leonard Craig, who was associated with union organizations in San Francisco, attempted to aid Mooney during the trial and worked to free him from prison. Many other organizations and individuals sought unsuccessfully to obtain a new trial for Mooney. For 22 years, Mooney remained in San Quentin prison while successive Governors resisted appeals for a pardon. In January 1939, Governor Culbert L. Olson of California gave Mooney an unconditional pardon. Billings was not officially pardoned until 1961 although he was freed by commutation of sentence in October 1939.
Scope and Content Note
This collection spans the years 1921-1938 and consists of correspondence, financial transactions, audit reports, resolutions, flyers, news releases, booklets, scrapbooks and newspaper articles.
The correspondence file contains copies of letters sent to Governor James Rolph of California from individuals, as well as labor unions, protesting Mooney's incarceration and demanding an unconditional pardon. It also contains flyers, newsletters, and a reprint of the front pages of The Bulletin, a San Francisco newspaper dated May 1, June 26 and 29, 1917.
Folders 2-4 contain original letters of introduction for Leonard Craig, a member of the Molders Local 164 of San Francisco, who toured the country seeking funds and support for Thomas Mooney. Folders 4 and 5 contain small scrapbooks with original letters of introduction.
Folders 6-8 contain transcripts of newspaper articles from December 1931 to May 1932. Folder 9 contains original clippings from various press clipping services.
This collection also contains pamphlets published by groups and individuals who believed in Mooney and Billings' innocence. Most of the information in these publications recounts the perjured testimony and frame-up of Mooney and Billings and subsequent court decisions regarding the case.
Four original scrapbooks with newspaper articles are located in Oversized Box 1. Folders 21-27 contain copies of the articles, which contain news of Mooney's trial and efforts by labor unions and prominent individuals to pardon him.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
The files are grouped into 3 series:
Missing Title
I, General
II, Pamphlets
III, Scrapbooks
Scrapbooks.; Clippings.; San Francisco (Ca.); Fliers (printed matter); Labor movement -- California.; Correspondence.; Socialism -- United States.; Trials -- Individual.; Olson, Cuthbert L.; National Mooney-Billings Committee; Symes, Lillian.; Schall, Thomas D.; Mooney Defense Committee of Greater Boston; Minor, Robert.; Mooney, Thomas J., 1882-1942.; Mooney Defense Committee of Southern California; International Molders' Union of North America; Griffin, Franklin A.; Billings, Warren K., 1893-197; Langdon, William H.; International Workers Defense League; California. Governor, (Cuthbert L. Olson); California Supreme Court; California. Governor, (James Rolph); American Civil Liberties Union; Young, C. C.; Whiting, Randolph V.; Blackstone, Robert.; Tom Mooney Molders Defense Committee; California Advisory Pardon Board
- General, 39399
  - Correspondence, 1931-1932; 39407 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General
    includes correspondance to and from Mooney. Including three letters retrieved from Herb Janick's files in 2018. Some items were removed in 2018 from this folder and moved to the Press folders. Press releases added to folder 18-19.
  - Leonard Craig, 1921-1931; 39406 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - Financial Transactions, 1931-1932; 39405 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    Contains monthly summaries of financial transactions by A. Schapiro. 3 summaries were added in 2018 from Herb Janick's files; two of the summaries were duplicates and were discarded.
  - Newspaper Articles (transcripts), 1931-1935; 39404 (Box 1, Folder 6-8)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1931-1935; 39403 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Press Releases, 1931-1935; 39402 (Box 1, Folder 18-19)
    Two Press releases added from Herb Janick's files in 2018.
  - Resolutions, 1931-1932; 39401 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Tom Mooney Defense Conference of Greater Boston, 1931; 39400 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Mooney-Billings button, undated; 57792 (Box OS 1, Item *)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Purchased via eBay (2/2014) not part of original collection.
  - AP photographs, 1930-1939; 57820; 11 photographs August 20, 1935 (Mooney, Billings and Clarence A. Larking(Warden)) July 12, 1930 (John C. Tailber) January 13, 1939 (Mooney and Billings) November 30, 1939 (Mooney) October 3, 1935 (Maxwell McNutt(Judge)) July 23, 1930 (Rena Mooney) April 28, 1933 (Frank P. Walsh and Leo Gallagher (Defense Attorneys)) January 12, 1939 (Tom and Rena Mooney) September 19, 1935 (Charles Goff (Police Lieut.), Mooney, Wilber Pengally (Sergt)) April 10, 1948 (Mooney and Court Smith (Warden)) January 10, 1939 (Mooney) (Box OS 1, Folder 1)
    Purchased via ebay, Feb 2014; 8 additional photographs purchased via ebay, Feb 2017
- Pamphlets, 39390
  - The Scandal of Mooney and Billings. The Decisions of The California Supreme Court, The Advisory Pardon Board, Governor Young denying pardons to Mooney and Billings. New York: National Mooney-Billings Committee, 1931; Synopsis of Minutes of Meeting of Executive Board, held at Cincinnati, Ohio, May 18th to 29th, inclusive, 1931. International Molders Union of America. 1931; Blackstone, Robert. By Their Deeds. New Orleans: Mooney Defense of Dixie. 1931., 39398 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Whiting, Randolph V., ed. California Decisions. "The Billings Pardon Reports" Part 2, vol. 81, No. 4264, p. 3-72., 1931; 39397 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Symes, Lillian. "Our American Dreyfus Case, A Challenge to California Justice." Harpers Magazine, 1931; Labor Leaders Betray Tom Mooney. 1931., 39396 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Governor Young: "Pardon Tom Mooney. He is innocent" by Judge Franklin A. Griffin. San Francisco: Tom Mooney Molders Defense Committee. 1929; Governor Young: "Pardon Tom Mooney. He is innocent" by Judge Franklin A. Griffin. San Francisco: Tom Mooney Molders Defense Committee. 1930., 1929-1930; 39395 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Mr. Justice Langdon Dissents. A New Chapter in the Mooney-Billings Case. New York: Arbitrator Press. 1930; Tom Mooney? San Francisco: Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee. 1931; Just***ice for Tom Mooney, who cries out from his tomb for help. San Francisco: Tom Mooney Molders' Defense Committee. 1931., 1930-1931; 39394 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Tom Mooney….Betrayed by Labor Leaders. San Francisco: Tom Mooney Molders Defense Committee., 1931; 39393 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Tom Mooney to Hang Aug. 23, 1918. nd; Minor, Robert. The Frame-Up System Story of the San Francisco Bomb. San Francisco: International Workers Defense League. 1916; Justice Is Waiting. California: San Francisco News. Reprint by Mooney Defense of Southern California. 1930., 1916-1930; 39392 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Schall, Thomas D. Why Is Mooney In Prison? Remarks of Hon. David I. Walsh of Massachusetts in the Senate of the United States, May 22, 1929. D.C. 1929; Young, C. C. Reprieves, Commutations and Pardons, 1927-1928. Sacramento: California State Printing Office. 1929., 39391 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Free Tom Mooney Street Run-Flier, undated (Box 1, Folder 17.1)
    Materials retrieved from Herb Janick's files in 2018.
  - Modern Thinker, 1932 (Box 1, Folder 17.2)
    Retrieved from Herb Janick's files in 2018.
  - Miscellaneous fliers and pamphlets, 1931-1932 (Box 1, Folder 17.3)
    Includes two items previously contained in correspondence folder and two items from Herb Janick's files. Includes "Stoning the Prophet's" by H.J. Hahn; a published receipts and disbursements pamphlet.
  - Poster with San Francisco Bulletin Facsimile, 1935 (Box OS 1, Folder os folder 1, Item 1)
- Scrapbooks, 39381
  - Scrapbook 1 (copy), 1931-1932; 39389 (Box 1, Folder 21-22)
  - Scrapbook 1 (original), 1931-1932; 39388 (Box OS 1, Item scrapbook1)
  - Scrapbook 2 (copy), 1932; 39387 (Box 1, Folder 23-24)
  - Scrapbook 2 (original), 1932; 39386 (Box OS 1, Item srapbook2)
  - Scrapbook 3 (copy), 1932; 39385 (Box 1, Folder 25-26)
  - Scrapbook 3 (original), 1932; 39384 (Box OS 1, Item scrapbook3)
  - Scrapbook 4 (copy), 1932; 39383 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Scrapbook 4 (original), 1932-1938; 39382 (Box OS 1, Item scrapbook4)
  - Full Page from San Francisco News, November 28, 1932 (Box OS 1, Folder os 1, Item 2)
    Numerous articles on the Mooney fram-up.